<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><atom:link href="https://marko.euptera.com/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><title>Marko Kocić Blog</title><link>https://marko.euptera.com/</link><description>Personal web site, blog, etc, ...</description><lastBuildDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2019 14:28:40 +0200</lastBuildDate><generator>clj-rss</generator><item><guid>https://marko.euptera.com/posts/2019-10-22-Add-Root-Certificate-to-Java-Keystore.html</guid><link>https://marko.euptera.com/posts/2019-10-22-Add-Root-Certificate-to-Java-Keystore.html</link><title>Add Root Certificate to Java Keystore</title><description>&lt;div class="sect2"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="_ssl_certificates"&gt;SSL Certificates&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="paragraph"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It certainly happened to you that you want to use your Java based application to connect to some https resource which doesn&amp;#8217;t have a valid or trusted certificate. While https and SSL certeficates are used to make sure that the site you connect to is trusted, sometimes you may want to override that settings and proclaim that the site with the given (self signed, invalid, &amp;#8230;&amp;#8203;) certificate is secure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="paragraph"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This can be done quite easy by adding that certificate to the Java certificate trust store.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="paragraph"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All you need is a keytool command that comes with the Java Development Kit and the certificate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="paragraph"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The easiest way to get the actual certificate is to open the https url in your browser and export certificate from there into the, i.e cert1.cer file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="paragraph"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then all you need is to execute the following command:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="listingblock"&gt;
&lt;div class="content"&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight"&gt;&lt;code&gt;keytool -import -trustcacerts -keystore keystore1.p12 -alias cert1_alias -file exported_cert.cer&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="paragraph"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that&amp;#8217;s basically it. The keytool will ask you for the keystore password and confirmation if you are sure what you are doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="paragraph"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From then on your Java program that uses given truststore will trust all certificates that you imported.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="paragraph"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BTW, if your application doesn&amp;#8217;t explicitly use it&amp;#8217;s own trust store, you can add your trusted certificate to the default Java CA store in a similar way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="listingblock"&gt;
&lt;div class="content"&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight"&gt;&lt;code&gt;keytool -import -trustcacerts -keystore $JAVA_HOME/jre/lib/security/cacerts -storepass changeit -alias cert1_alias -file exported_cert.cer&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="paragraph"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But be careful. This will make the certificate trusted to all application using given Java runtime environmtent, and this may not be what you want to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate></item><item><guid>https://marko.euptera.com/posts/2016-11-22-sticky-folders-on-linux.html</guid><link>https://marko.euptera.com/posts/2016-11-22-sticky-folders-on-linux.html</link><title>Sticky folders on Linux</title><description>&lt;h3 id="sticky&amp;#95;folders&amp;#95;on&amp;#95;linux"&gt;Sticky folders on Linux&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Every once in a while when developing something on Linux, I am facing the similar issues. The question is how to ensure that all files in a directory, regardless of who is creating them, are accessible by multiple users.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Obvious solution is to just assigne ownership of the files to some group, and give permissions to that group. Then, all users that are members of that group can access them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This works fine, until one of the users create a new file, or a new directory. In that case, he is the owner of that one file or disectory, and access by other users dependens on his default settings. Obviously, root can fix that by running chown and changing ownership again, but that's manual process.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Luckily, since we are running Linux, the solution exists:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# First change ownership of the current directory
chown -R user&amp;#95;1:group&amp;#95;1 ./somedir

# Set file ACL for the directory
setfacl -Rdm u::rwx,g::rwx ./somedir
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;From now on, every file and directory created in somedir will inherit group_1 as the primary group, thus be accessible to all group members.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now, we only need to make sure all files are accessible to that group, and noone else.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# All files should be readable and writable only to owner and group
find ./somedir -type f -exec chmod 660 {} + -o -type d -exec chmod 2770 {} +

# All executable should also be executable by all group members
find ./somedir -name &amp;quot;&amp;#42;.sh&amp;quot; -exec chmod 770 {} +
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;And that's basically it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;One of the common use cases would be when we have multiple users working on the same application. Then we can create a group and user for the project, set the ownership to the project directory to that group, and add all project members to the group. Then, they all can access the files there, as well as the application user running the application, without danger that they will create a file that application user don't have permission to read.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate></item><item><guid>https://marko.euptera.com/posts/2016-01-04-umatrix.html</guid><link>https://marko.euptera.com/posts/2016-01-04-umatrix.html</link><title>uMatrix and uBlock</title><description>&lt;h3 id="umatrix&amp;#95;and&amp;#95;ublock&amp;#95;origin"&gt;uMatrix and uBlock Origin&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since a few months I started using &lt;strong&gt;uBlock Origin&lt;/strong&gt; as a privacy plugin for Firefox. Although it works good, after some time it start to be annoying having to constantly tweak it. It's ok that it tries to be user friendly, but sometimes I just feel like too much tweaking is required to get a balance between privacy and having non-broken web browsing experience.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Then, I came across a new Firefox plugin by the same author as uBlock. It's called &lt;a href='https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/umatrix/'&gt;uMatrix&lt;/a&gt;. It allows for a nice matrix like UI to define the blocking and allow rules. It has sensible defaults, which provide nice tradeofs out of the box with minimal tweaking.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Right now, I'm using &lt;strong&gt;uMatrix&lt;/strong&gt; as my only ad blocker and tracker blocker tool on all my browsers. If you haven't tried it, just give it a go, you may never look back.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The only drawback is that it doesn't work on the Firefox version for Android, at least not yet.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Mon, 04 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate></item><item><guid>https://marko.euptera.com/posts/2015-11-10-jes-eur.html</guid><link>https://marko.euptera.com/posts/2015-11-10-jes-eur.html</link><title>Jes EÜR</title><description>&lt;h2 id="freelancing&amp;#95;requirements&amp;#95;in&amp;#95;germany"&gt;Freelancing requirements in Germany&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Being freelancer in Germany is not so simple as being freelancer in other parts of the world. It can be very complicated, especially for a beginner.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is not enough to just start working, and worry later about taxes, registration and other legalities. No, you first need to register yourself with the tax office. Then you need to make clear are you &lt;em&gt;Selbständig&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Freiberufler&lt;/em&gt;. While both can be translated as &lt;em&gt;freelancer&lt;/em&gt;, the obligation, legal requirements and bookkeeping differs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id="anlage&amp;#95;eür"&gt;Anlage EÜR&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although freelancers are not required to do full double entry accounting, like &lt;strong&gt;GMBH&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;UG&lt;/strong&gt;, they are required to report their earnings at the end of the year in a consolidated way, by submitting the so called &lt;strong&gt;Anlage-EÜR&lt;/strong&gt; to the tax office. Being Freiberufler, one is theoretically not required to fill in the form, but I heard all kind of stories that tax people don't like it when you make it more complicated to them, and not submitting Anlage-EÜR electronically is definitelly more work for them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id="jes-eür"&gt;Jes-EÜR&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of programs that allows one to do bookkeeping, most of them commercial, with varying quality and pricing. Working primarily on Linux, and not even owning a Windows machine, makes the choice much worse. Only a few of commercially available software support non-Windows platforms, and non-windows usually means Mac.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are a couple of online software packages, but they always seemed a bit limited compared to the full desktop version. And I don't like subscription model where I lose all data and convenience when I decide to stop paying for the service.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Then I came around the &lt;a href='http://jes-eur.de/'&gt;Jes-Eür&lt;/a&gt;. It's a nice Java based cross platform program that allows to track income and expenses, categorize them in the standard categories, and provide a report that can be used to submit Anlage-EÜR. Granted, it is missing an option to automatically submit it to the tax office, but it provides printout with explanation that would make filling in the form on the official tax department web site a two minutes of effor. I even like it more that way, since it gives an impression of the control during the process.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 10 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate></item><item><guid>https://marko.euptera.com/posts/2015-11-03-morning.html</guid><link>https://marko.euptera.com/posts/2015-11-03-morning.html</link><title>Week day morning</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Today while walking from the train station to the office I had to stop to admire the view.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/img/2015-11-03-morning.png" alt="image morning" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Living in one of the most industrially developed cities in the world while still having opportuntity for a nice stroll through the nature has its merits.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate></item><item><guid>https://marko.euptera.com/posts/2015-10-29-improved-privacy.html</guid><link>https://marko.euptera.com/posts/2015-10-29-improved-privacy.html</link><title>Quickly improve web browsing privacy</title><description>&lt;p&gt;While browsing Hacker News &lt;a href='https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=10470535'&gt;thread&lt;/a&gt; just got to this small tip for improving web browsing privacy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I use Firefox and install the following:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Disconnect&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Ublock Origin (choose 3rd-Party block lists to suit.)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Privacy Badger (no set up, just install, it learns as you go)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;In Firefox, use about:config to change the following:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Toggle dom.storage.enabled to False&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Toggle layout.css.visited&lt;i&gt;links&lt;/i&gt;enabled to False&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Toggle media.peerconnection.enabled to False&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Toggle network.prefetch-next to False&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Toggle network.http.sendReferrerHeader to 0 (zero)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Toggle network.http.sendSecureXSiteReferrer to False&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;These settings have worked for me with no issues. I bank, do all manner of things online with no issues. I do, however, see no ads, no tracking, faster page loads, clean experience all around.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not sure if it would be too paranoid, but there's no real drawbacks trying it. While the advice is about Firefox, I'm sure something similar could be achieved with Chrome, at least to some extent.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 29 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate></item><item><guid>https://marko.euptera.com/posts/2015-10-02-markdown-vs-asciidoc.html</guid><link>https://marko.euptera.com/posts/2015-10-02-markdown-vs-asciidoc.html</link><title>Markdown vs Asciidoc</title><description>&lt;p&gt;While playing around with this &lt;a href='http://cryogenweb.org'&gt;Cryogen&lt;/a&gt; based blog genertor, very soon I hit the limit. It was very easy to get started, I even put some (moderate) effort and very quickly adapted my &lt;a href='/pages/marko-kocic-cv.html'&gt;CV&lt;/a&gt; using Markdown syntax.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The process is very easy. Just copy the content from the web page, paste it to the new file, and adapt a few things to fit the Markdown syntax. The resulting page looks quite usable, except for the few details. For example, in the "Personal data" section it is not possible to have picture on the left side, and personal details on the right. Also, I'd prefer to have columns aligned there. It's a small thing, a matter of preference, but those small things can become annoying pretty quickly.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That would be a perfect case for HTML tables, but Markdwn, as basic as it is, doesn't support table-like formatting. After looking around a bit, I found out that Asciidoc do support tables, as well as manu other more advance formatting options. It is so similar to Markdown, that could even be considered as a superset of it. Except that it isn't. There are some changes, namely the links formatting and few more small things. I'd like to give it a try, but I'm too lazy to convert all of my content here (all three pages).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cryogen does support both Markdown and Asciidoc, but not the mixture. You either need one or another for all pages and blog posts. I can't see a reason why it couldn't distinguish the engine type by file extension, and allow for mixed sources. I think I would just open a Cryogen feature request and see if someone else is interested in it. I may even do it myself when I find some time, but I'm sure people already familiar with the code base would do it much faster.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Update: The Github issue to allow different formats for  individual pages is &lt;a href='https://github.com/cryogen-project/cryogen-core/issues/48'&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Fri, 02 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate></item><item><guid>https://marko.euptera.com/posts/2015-10-01-first-post.html</guid><link>https://marko.euptera.com/posts/2015-10-01-first-post.html</link><title>First Post</title><description>&lt;h3 id="this&amp;#95;is&amp;#95;my&amp;#95;first&amp;#95;post!"&gt;This is my first post!&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;I have been playing around with the idea of finally updating my "Home Page". Before, it was only my CV hosted on the Google AppEngine, but it became kindo of annoying to update it regularly.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I was thinking about setting up something simpler. Didn't like the idea of having to set up the whole full featured blogging platform like Wordpress or similar. I wanted something simlpe, something that I could easily update, preferably using any text editor, and which wouldn't require more than Apache web server to host it. Thus, I started looking at static web site generators.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When I came around the &lt;a href='http://cryogenweb.org'&gt;Cryogen&lt;/a&gt;, I was sold. It looked exactly what I needed, so I decided to start my personal "site" using it.&lt;/p&gt;</description><pubDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate></item></channel></rss>