<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><atom:link href="https://marko.euptera.com/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><title>Marko Kocić Blog</title><link>https://marko.euptera.com/</link><description>Personal web site, blog, etc, ...</description><lastBuildDate>Tue, 05 May 2020 13:22:05 +0200</lastBuildDate><generator>clj-rss</generator><item><guid>https://marko.euptera.com/posts/2019-10-22-Add-Root-Certificate-to-Java-Keystore.html</guid><link>https://marko.euptera.com/posts/2019-10-22-Add-Root-Certificate-to-Java-Keystore.html</link><title>Add Root Certificate to Java Keystore</title><description>SSL CertificatesIt certainly happened to you that you want to use your Java-based application to connect to some https resource which doesn’t have a valid or trusted certificate. While https and SSL certificates are used to make sure that the site you connect to is trusted, sometimes you may want to override that settings and proclaim that the site with the given (self signed, invalid, …​) certificate is secure.This can be done quite easy by adding that certificate to the Java certificate trust store.All you need is a keytool command that comes with the Java Development Kit and the certificate.The easiest way to get the actual certificate is to open the https url in your browser and export certificate from there into the cert1.cer file.Then all you need is to execute the following command:And that’s basically it. The keytool will ask you for the keystore password and confirmation if you are sure what you are doing.From then on your Java program that uses given truststore will trust all certificates that you imported.BTW, if your application doesn’t explicitly use it’s own trust store, you can add your trusted certificate to the default Java CA store in a similar way.But be careful. This will make the certificate trusted to all application using given Java runtime environment, and this may not be what you want to do.</description><pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate></item><item><guid>https://marko.euptera.com/posts/2016-11-22-sticky-folders-on-linux.html</guid><link>https://marko.euptera.com/posts/2016-11-22-sticky-folders-on-linux.html</link><title>Sticky folders on Linux</title><description>Sticky folders on LinuxEvery once in a while when developing something on Linux, I am facing the similar issues. The question is how to ensure that all files in a directory, regardless of who is creating them, are accessible by multiple users.</description><pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate></item><item><guid>https://marko.euptera.com/posts/2016-01-04-umatrix.html</guid><link>https://marko.euptera.com/posts/2016-01-04-umatrix.html</link><title>uMatrix and uBlock</title><description>uMatrix and uBlock OriginSince a few months I started using uBlock Origin as a privacy plugin for Firefox. Although it works good, after some time it start to be annoying having to constantly tweak it. It's ok that it tries to be user friendly, but sometimes I just feel like too much tweaking is required to get a balance between privacy and having non-broken web browsing experience.</description><pubDate>Mon, 04 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate></item><item><guid>https://marko.euptera.com/posts/2015-11-10-jes-eur.html</guid><link>https://marko.euptera.com/posts/2015-11-10-jes-eur.html</link><title>Jes EÜR</title><description>Freelancing requirements in GermanyBeing freelancer in Germany is not so simple as being freelancer in other parts of the world. It can be very complicated, especially for a beginner.</description><pubDate>Tue, 10 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate></item><item><guid>https://marko.euptera.com/posts/2015-11-03-morning.html</guid><link>https://marko.euptera.com/posts/2015-11-03-morning.html</link><title>Week day morning</title><description>Today while walking from the train station to the office I had to stop to admire the view.</description><pubDate>Tue, 03 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate></item><item><guid>https://marko.euptera.com/posts/2015-10-29-improved-privacy.html</guid><link>https://marko.euptera.com/posts/2015-10-29-improved-privacy.html</link><title>Quickly improve web browsing privacy</title><description>While browsing Hacker News thread just got to this small tip for improving web browsing privacy.I use Firefox and install the following:</description><pubDate>Thu, 29 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate></item><item><guid>https://marko.euptera.com/posts/2015-10-02-markdown-vs-asciidoc.html</guid><link>https://marko.euptera.com/posts/2015-10-02-markdown-vs-asciidoc.html</link><title>Markdown vs Asciidoc</title><description>While playing around with this Cryogen based blog generator, very soon I hit the limit. It was easy to get started, I even put some (moderate) effort and quickly adapted my CV using Markdown syntax.The process is straightforward. Just copy the content from the web page, paste it to the new file, and adapt a few things to fit the Markdown syntax. The resulting page looks quite usable, except for the few details. For example, in the "Personal data" section it is not possible to have a picture on the left side, and personal details on the right. Also, I'd prefer columns aligned there. It's a small thing, a matter of preference, but those small things can become annoying pretty quickly.</description><pubDate>Fri, 02 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate></item><item><guid>https://marko.euptera.com/posts/2015-10-01-first-post.html</guid><link>https://marko.euptera.com/posts/2015-10-01-first-post.html</link><title>First Post</title><description>This is my first post!I have been playing around with the idea of finally updating my "Home Page". Before, it was only my CV hosted on the Google AppEngine, but it became kind of annoying to update it regularly.</description><pubDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate></item></channel></rss>